Guide to the Gertrude Hoffmann Collection BCMS.0018
Brooklyn Collection
Gertrude Hoffmann collection
1905-1945
Brooklyn Collection
Gertrude Hoffmann Company.
Gertrude Hoffmann Girls.
Hoffmann, Gertrude
BCMS.0018
5.1 Linear feet in 5 boxes
A collection of photographs, news clippings, and scrapbooks related to the dancer and choreographer Gertrude Hoffmann and her dance troupe the Gertrude Hoffmann Girls.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
This collection was given to Brooklyn Public Library prior to the Brooklyn Collection's founding and the details of its provenance are unknown. The photographs of Ann Sweeney, a dancer in Hoffmann's troupe, were donated to the collection by Sweeney's grandniece Ginger Murphy in 2017.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series by type of material. Series I: Documents contains lists of Hoffmann's "Experiences and Credits" as well as letters from and regarding her son Max Hoffmann, Jr. Series II consists of Photographs of Gertrude Hoffmann arranged roughly chronologically and foldered by photographer. Series III is Photographs of the Gertrude Hoffmann Girls, with three subseries: Individual Portraits, Group Photographs, and Rehearsal and Performance Photographs. Each subseries is arranged roughly chronologically. Series IV is Personal Photographs, including family photographs. Series V: Newspaper and Magazine Clippings is arranged chronologically. Series VI: Ephemera includes posters, advertisements, and other ephemera. Series VII: Scrapbooks contains two scrapbooks compiled by Hoffmann.
Biographical Note
American vaudeville dancer and choreographer Gertrude Hoffmann (sometimes spelled Hoffman) was born Catherine Gertrude Hayes on May 7, 1885 in San Francisco, California, to parents John and Catherine Hayes. At her mother's urging, Gertrude – whose early stage name was "Kitty" – took dancing lessons as a young girl and soon began auditioning for roles in the local theaters. She made her vaudeville debut in 1899 at Frederic Belasco's Alcazar Theatre. Gertrude met composer and arranger Max Hoffmann while touring as a dancer, and two married in 1901. Hoffmann gave birth to a son, Max Jr., in 1902.
Hoffmann started out as a dancer and impressionist on the vaudeville stage; in her early years she performed imitations of other, more famous performers, including Eva Tanguay and Anna Held. Hoffmann worked with the latter in Flo Ziegfeld's A Parisian Model in 1906, shocking many by dressing in drag and dancing with Held. Programs from Hoffmann's appearances on Brooklyn stages during this period can be found in our Brooklyn Playbills and Programs Collection. She made her first major impression on audiences in 1908, with her rendition of the then-popular "Dance of the Seven Veils," adapted from the biblical story of Salome. Hoffmann was repeatedly arrested when touring the United States with the dance, although some historians suggest that the arrests were arranged by vaudeville impresario Oscar Hammerstein to drum up publicity. Despite the scandals, this period marked Hoffmann's change of focus from dancing as entertainment to dancing as a high art. Hoffmann also gained fame when she partnered with theatrical producer Morris Guest to introduce American audiences to the much-lauded Russian ballet company, the Ballets Russes, in 1911 by hiring European dancers to perform pieces from the company, albeit without choreographer Michel Fokine's permission.
Hoffmann continued to perform through the 1910s, although by the mid-1920s she had largely given up her role as a dancer to concentrate instead on directing and choreographing her own group. She formed the Gertrude Hoffmann Girls dance troupe during this time – a chorus line of 18 to 25 dancing girls whose stage act also included fencing and aerial acrobatics. This group performed on New York stages as well as at Paris's famed Moulin Rouge nightclub through the mid-1930s.
Hoffmann largely disappeared from the stage after the 1930s. She died of a heart attack on October 21, 1966, in Hollywood, California, following the death of her husband and collaborator, Max Hoffmann, in 1963.
Sources:
Cullen, Frank, Florence Hackman, and Donald McNeilly. "Gertrude Hoffmann" Vaudeville, Old & New: An Encyclopedia of Variety Performers in America. New York: Routledge, 2007.
Fields, Armond. Women Vaudeville Stars: Eighty Biographical Profiles. Jefferson, N.C: McFarland, 2006.
Gertrude Hoffmann obituary. Dance magazine. December, 1966.
Kendall, Elizabeth. Where She Danced. New York: Knopf, 1979.
Mordden, Ethan. Ziegfeld: The Man Who Invented Show Business. New York: St. Martin's Press, 2008.
Trav S D. No Applause, Just Throw Money, Or, the Book That Made Vaudeville Famous: A High-Class, Refined Entertainment. New York: Faber and Faber, 2005.
Related Materials
At the Brooklyn Collection:
Brooklyn Playbills and Programs Collection
Hoffmann, Gertrude biographical file, Brooklyn Collection reference section
Other resources:
The Gertrude and Max Hoffmann Papers. Wake Forest University, Z. Smith Reynolds Library.
Gertrude Hoffmann Clippings, 1910-1927 and Gertrude Hoffmann Programs. New York Public Library, Jerome Robbins Dance Division.
Gertrude Hoffmann materials at the Museum of the City of New York
Harry Ransom Center
Shields, David S. Broadway Photographs. A website with information about theatrical photographers and studios and the performers they documented.
Shubert Archive
Scope and Contents
The Gertrude Hoffmann Collection covers the period from 1905 to 1945, which roughly coincides with the span of Hoffmann's professional career. The collection consists largely of publicity photographs of Hoffmann herself and of her troupe, the Gertrude Hoffmann Girls, including both studio photographs and images of performances. There are several headshots of individual performers from the Gertrude Hoffmann Girls. Two scrapbooks, presumably compiled by Hoffmann herself, include snapshots, newspaper clippings, and ephemera from the Hoffmann Girls' European tours. Although there is little coverage of Hoffmann's personal life in the collection, it does contain several photographs and letters of her son, Max Hoffmann, Jr. and some additional family photographs. Programs and articles from the Gertrude Hoffmann Girls' European tours are often in French, sometimes with English annotations by Hoffmann.
Choreographers; Dancers; Stage photography; Vaudeville; Women choreographers; Women dancers
- Series I: Documents
  - Max Hoffmann, Jr. letters and writings, circa 1910s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Experiences and Credits, circa 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Typed review of Gertrude Hoffmann Girls performance in Nice, , circa 1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Photographs of Gertrude Hoffmann
  - Otto Sarony Co. portraits, circa 1910s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    General
    Includes a photograph of Hoffmann dressed as Eve Tanguay.
  - Frank C. Bangs portraits, circa 1910-1913 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - White Studio portraits I, circa 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes a photograph of Hoffmann dressed as Anna Held.
  - Mixed professional portraits, circa 1910s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes portraits by James & Bushnell (Seattle) and Canell (NY), as well as two postcards of Hoffmann.
  - Kuhli portraits (peacock costume), circa 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jean de Strelecki portraits, circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Herbert Mitchell portraits, circa 1928-1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hall's Studio portraits, circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Otto Sarony Co. portraits (oversize), circa 1910s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Frank C. Bangs beach portraits, circa 1913 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - White Studio portraits II & III, circa 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Dietz photos, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Apeda portraits, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series III: Photographs of the Gertrude Hoffmann Girls
  - Subseries 1: Individual Portraits
    - Ann Sweeney photos, circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bloom portraits, 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Empire portraits, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Mixed individual portraits, circa 1930s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Full body portraits (Box 2, Folder 8)
      By Waléry (circa 1925), Celebrity (circa 1920s), and Canell (1930s).
    - Canell headshots, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2: Group Photographs
    - Travel photographs, 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Mixed publicity photographs, 1920s-1930s (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Includes images of Hoffmann with the girls.
  - Subseries 3: Rehearsal and Performance Photographs
    - Waléry stage photos, circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Mixed performance photos, 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Some have Hoffmann's notes on the versos.
    - Brighton Hippodrome backstage photographs, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Balloon Barrage" performance, circa 1920s (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Sword Routine, circa 1934 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Rehearsal photographs of acrobatic routine by Arthur Sasse, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Personal Photographs
  - Photographs of Max Hoffmann, Jr., circa 1905-1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mixed personal photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes an image of the vaudeville performers Mary Marble and Sam "Little" Chip in blackface for the musical play Tuxedo, signed on the verso "To Max and Gertie."
  - Mixed personal photographs (oversize), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series V: Newspaper and Magazine Clippings
  - Clippings, 1905-1910 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes a clipping about Max Hoffmann, Jr. and caricatures of Gertrude Hoffmann by Marius de Zayas.
  - Clippings, January 1913 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, September 1913 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, October 1913 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, November 1913 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, December 1913 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1915-1920 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, 1925-1927 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Clippings, 1935-1939 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Includes clippings about Max Hoffmann, Jr.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Series VI: Ephemera
  - Ideas for Numbers, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 17, Cabinet Morgue Flat File 1, Drawer 12)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes clippings, prints, sketches and notes related to ideas for dance numbers, including an oversize sketch of the stage layout for a number involving parachutes, possibly inspired by a 1941 clipping of parachuting soldiers.
  - Gertrude Hoffmann ephemera, 1908-1913 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Includes a program, menu, and postcard.
  - Gertrude Hoffmann Girls ephemera, circa 1933-1939 (Box 3, Folder 19, Cabinet Morgue Flat File 1, Drawer 12)
    Includes an envelope, poster, flyer, programs, and an oversize poster for the Girls' August 1939 appearance at the Brighton Hippodrome.
- Series VII: Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook I, 1934 (Box 4)
    Photographs and clippings from the Gertrude Hoffmann Girls' European travels in 1934. Many of the clippings are duplicated in Series V.
  - Scrapbook II, 1921-1922 (Box 5)
    Newspaper clippings from 1921 and 1922. This scrapbook originally contained additional clippings through 1933, but at the time of processing they were loose, out of order, and, in many cases, damaged. They have been photocopied and foldered in Series V.